<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>exploration | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/exploration/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/exploration/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>exploration</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 22:13:05 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/images/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>exploration</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/exploration/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eastshade</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-eastshade/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 22:13:05 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-eastshade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The opening hour of &lt;em&gt;Eastshade&lt;/em&gt; charades as yet another open-world role-playing game with bad physics and fetch quests but the hope for a decent, rustic-medieval-fantasy story.
&amp;ldquo;From these humble beginnings, I&amp;rsquo;ll make my heroic mark on this world,&amp;rdquo; you say to yourself as you arrive in the game&amp;rsquo;s charming but somewhat prototypical starting village.
But &lt;em&gt;Eastshade&lt;/em&gt;, dear reader, is not a fantasy island through which to blaze a fiery campaign of blood and magic; rather, it asks you to find joy in drinking herbal teas and riding a penny-farthing through the forest to find the perfect vista to capture on your canvas.
As a professional painter in a fully nonviolent world, an easel and brush replace sword and sorcery as you quest to capture your late mother&amp;rsquo;s favorite sights on the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TODO: picture?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory, an experience emphasizing non-violence and exploring role-playing-as-a-painter should have been a fresh take that I&amp;rsquo;d fall for.
Instead, for a game that uses literal inspiration as currency for your character&amp;rsquo;s painting capabilities, I completed &lt;em&gt;Eastshade&lt;/em&gt; feeling markedly uninspired.
Freedom from the shackles of combat-oriented game design could have opened entirely new directions for innovative play, but &lt;em&gt;Eastshade&lt;/em&gt; feels like it has a combat-shaped hole someone forgot to fill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emphasizing relationships and conversation could have played out as intricate, interconnected social drama to immerse in, but interactinos in &lt;em&gt;Eastshade&lt;/em&gt; primarily drives fetch quests that only occasionally involve painting, the game&amp;rsquo;s crowning mechanic.
And — while perhaps I&amp;rsquo;m just picky — a game about painting should have tried a little harder on graphics and art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s basically  phototourism with the occasionally intriguing conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eastshade&lt;/em&gt; is an open-world role-playing game that casts the player as a professional painter visiting their late mother&amp;rsquo;s favorite island getaway.
In a quest to honor your mother&amp;rsquo;s memory by painting her favorite places in Eastshade, you meet and help a reasonably sized cast of the island&amp;rsquo;s anthropomorphic animal inhabitants.
Some want you to paint their favorite things, some need to get out of debt, and some just want a friend.
In theory, an experience that emphasizes non-violence and explores role-playing-as-a-painter should have been a fresh and interesting take I&amp;rsquo;d have fallen for.
Instead, for a game that uses literal inspiration as currency for your character&amp;rsquo;s painting capabilities, I was left feeling markedly uninspired.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
