<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>videography | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/videography/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/videography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>videography</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 12:15:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/media/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>videography</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/videography/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oh, the Places You&#39;ll Go</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/post/oh-the-places-youll-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 12:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/post/oh-the-places-youll-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student, I get to travel quite a bit. In just the last two years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been to Atlanta (a few times, once as a visiting researcher to GaTech for 3 months), Austin, Vienna, Dagstuhl, and — most recently — Tokyo. I get to meet interesting researchers on every trip, whether it be during a conference coffee break (where &amp;ldquo;meeting&amp;rdquo; people occasionally feels like getting interrogated about research) or by running into each other while meandering through a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.japan-guide.com/e/e3034_001.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;national park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vyza5tbx-qc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These trips are largely work. I listen to talks on the latest research and imagine ways to connect them to my own. I introduce myself to more senior researchers (usually hesitantly) in the hopes that they&amp;rsquo;ll remember who I am once they&amp;rsquo;re through answering my questions. I stay up way too late the night before my talk polishing my slides to (what I hope is) perfection. I scribble all over whiteboards, drawing (mostly) intelligible pictures when working out new ideas with collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Need to update &amp;ldquo;slides&amp;rdquo; with a link to the talk I gave at WSSR.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then there&amp;rsquo;s the beauty of getting to go to new places &lt;em&gt;because I have to&lt;/em&gt;. As an introvert and someone who&amp;rsquo;s pretty happy being in one place, travel is definitely not an itch I need to scratch (to me, &amp;ldquo;wanderlust&amp;rdquo; often feels like a made up word fellow Millennials use to describe the need for jealousy-inducing Instagram content). But my PhD has helped me learn that there&amp;rsquo;s a lot out there to see and understand, and somehow the difference and uncertainty and novelty of it all makes me feel hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, until we meet again, Tokyo.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
