<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>action | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/action/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/action/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>action</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2020 12:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/images/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>action</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/action/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Star Wars: The Clone Wars</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/movie-star-wars-the-clone-wars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2020 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/movie-star-wars-the-clone-wars/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It really isn&amp;rsquo;t fair to watch an early Extended Universe entry like &lt;em&gt;Star Wars: The Clone Wars&lt;/em&gt; in 2020 after we&amp;rsquo;ve been given the gift of the Abrams-Johnson sequel trilogy. If modern &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; were to be described developmentally, then the original trilogy is its stellar parents, the prequel trilogy is its stumbling childhood, and this movie is its awkward pre-teen years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Clone Wars&lt;/em&gt; kicks off in the thick of a broader conflict set in the Outer Rim. The Hutts control the trade routes and thus the supply lines in the area. The Separatists, led by Count Dooku (and Palpatine, of course, on the down low), hatch a plan to kidnap Jabba the Hutt&amp;rsquo;s son and frame the Jedi for it. Obi-Wan, Anakin, and Anakin&amp;rsquo;s new Padawan Ahsoka set out to save Jabba&amp;rsquo;s son. And&amp;hellip; that&amp;rsquo;s pretty much it. 80% of this movie is repetitive clone-droid battles, another 10% is lightsaber battles, and in the last 10% you get heavy-handed &amp;ldquo;banter&amp;rdquo; dressed up as character development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; mainstays are a crutch this film leans far too heavily on, refusing to take risks with its narrative. &lt;em&gt;The Clone Wars&lt;/em&gt; serves up a buffet of Jawas, a brief C-3PO cameo, Tatooine, the Mos Eisley jazz band, Obi-Wan&amp;rsquo;s circle light speed ship thing, lots of holographic intercoms, etc. all trying to hide the obvious: the world didn&amp;rsquo;t ask for an animated &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; movie. Only two years after &lt;em&gt;Revenge of the Sith&lt;/em&gt;, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to even say this strategy wins any points in the nostalgia category. Instead, we&amp;rsquo;re left with a whole lot of nothing dressed up in royal clothes. It almost feels like sacrilege to hear the Skywalker theme played as often as it is here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not to say there aren&amp;rsquo;t good moments. This is the first entry in the &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt; universe to have the droids talk as far as I remember, and it makes for some self-aware humor that the later movies definitely iterated on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Droid 1: &amp;ldquo;Concentrate fire on Sector 11374265!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Droid 2: &amp;ldquo;1137— what was that again?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Droid 1, grabbing the other one&amp;rsquo;s head and pointing: &amp;ldquo;Just fire right there!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;em&gt;Star Wars: The Clone Wars&lt;/em&gt;, 34:32&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between Anakin and Ahsoka is also nice, when it&amp;rsquo;s not corny. Anakin even shows some level-headed maturity and humility in reminding Ahsoka that she doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to prove herself to anyone. There&amp;rsquo;s a nice touch of psychological safety and assurance there (though it seems totally constructed when compared to his raging tantrums in Episodes II and III).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also worth mentioning that the portrayal of women in this movie is painful (though it was 2007). At one point, a droid addressing Ventress — Count Dooku&amp;rsquo;s apprentice — accidentally salutes her as &amp;ldquo;sir&amp;rdquo; and then stumbles to correct itself, only to again call her &amp;ldquo;sir.&amp;rdquo; Obi-Wan condescendingly refers to her as &amp;ldquo;darling&amp;rdquo; in his British accent during a lightsaber duel, to which she just responds by clenching her teeth and growling. Anakin gets to play the aloof and displeased male around the baby Huttlet; Ahsoka does most of the caretaking and connecting with it. The Huttlet&amp;rsquo;s mom/Jabba&amp;rsquo;s partner, who you&amp;rsquo;d think would be concerned with this whole kidnapping situation, is not even present as a background character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, was this a good movie? Not really. But I&amp;rsquo;m interested to see how the TV series evolved over the next decade, and especially how it matures into the backdrop for &lt;em&gt;Rise of Skywalker&lt;/em&gt; that it so clearly is today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Batman: Arkham City</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-batman-arkham-city/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-batman-arkham-city/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I played &lt;em&gt;Arkham Asylum&lt;/em&gt; back in summer of 2015, so it somehow seems fitting for this much busier stage of my life that it took me four years to play the sequel. That being said, the gap I&amp;rsquo;ve taken from the &lt;em&gt;Batman: Arkham&lt;/em&gt; series may ultimately have been to my benefit, given just how similar &lt;em&gt;Arkham City&lt;/em&gt; feels to &lt;em&gt;Arkham Asylum&lt;/em&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;re still beating the crap out of every other living character in the game (who all seem inexplicably hostile towards us on sight), we&amp;rsquo;re still uncovering a diabolical plot that features an all-star cast of Batman villains, and we&amp;rsquo;re still tracking down every Riddler secret using every piece of WayneTech we can get our hands on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, all of it is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;. Very few superhero games, especially those being made back in the early 2010s, can hold a candle to the experience that &lt;em&gt;Arkham City&lt;/em&gt; provides. From gliding and grappling through the city to using detective mode to solve crimes, every moment feels like an authentic, exhilarating experience of donning the cape and cowl of the Dark Knight. Catwoman, Robin, and Nightwing are also playable characters for smaller segments, each with their own exciting gadgets and play styles. A huge amount of the game&amp;rsquo;s success can be credited to the immersive open-world of &lt;em&gt;Arkham City&lt;/em&gt;, greatly improving over the labyrinth Metroidvania-like level design of &lt;em&gt;Arkham Asylum&lt;/em&gt;. Adding a mix of outdoor and indoor locations to the game adds further opportunities for the mechanics and side missions to enrich the overall experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this brings me to a point of &lt;em&gt;Arkham City&lt;/em&gt; I was surprised by, and one that I would have only picked up on now, in 2019. Thanks to the open-world design, we get a lot of radio chatter from various inmates and characters to make the solo experience feel more alive. Most of what they say is fine but forgettable, like &amp;ldquo;I wonder what&amp;rsquo;s on TV right now,&amp;rdquo; or self-dating to an era where Facebook was still a novelty: &amp;ldquo;How am I supposed to update my status? &amp;hellip;Oh yeah, I&amp;rsquo;m still stuck here in this stinking prison.&amp;rdquo; But a lot of it hints at something much more sinister, not originating from the inmates themselves, but from their experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, the plot of the game is that Prof. Hugo Strange gets Gotham City to agree to a pretty bonkers plan wherein they wall off a huge part of the city, throw all the inmates and supervillains from Arkham Asylum inside, and seal it shut. Strange likes this because he gets to &amp;ldquo;study&amp;rdquo; the criminally insane (for the good of science, I&amp;rsquo;m sure), and because the prison is a perfect way of making sure anyone who knows the truth of his nefarious purposes (like Bruce Wayne) are never heard from again. But in an age where we&amp;rsquo;re talking a lot more about racial discrimination, police brutality, and other failures of our criminal justice system, you start to wonder why in the world Batman feels the need to be inside this prison, beating the pulp out of everyone he sees. A decent number of inmates will yell &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s Batman doing here?&amp;rdquo; when you start a fight. Others get picked up by your police scanner: &amp;ldquo;Why&amp;rsquo;s Batman in here anyway, aren&amp;rsquo;t we already locked up?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that a lot of these inmates are bad people, especially the more ruthless ones who work closely with the big bads (Penguin, Two-Face, Joker, etc.). But my guess is that a lot of the inmates joined up with some villain&amp;rsquo;s faction just so they had food to eat, or so they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t get killed in the streets. And while I know Batman will never be compassionate, I wonder if he couldn&amp;rsquo;t be just a bit more conscientious. Otherwise, I worry that Joker&amp;rsquo;s right when he says Batman belongs inside with the rest of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bugs&#34;&gt;Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game would occasionally crash with some pretty unreadable error messages, but was otherwise flawless.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thor: Ragnarok</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/movie-thor-ragnarok/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/movie-thor-ragnarok/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thor: Ragnarok&lt;/em&gt; came to finish what both &lt;em&gt;Guardians of the Galaxy&lt;/em&gt; films started. Instead of honing in on one hero&amp;rsquo;s dramatic story arc, &lt;em&gt;Ragnarok&lt;/em&gt; stars a group of them. The action takes us from planet to planet across all the known galaxy by spaceship and &lt;del&gt;wormhole&lt;/del&gt; anus. But most importantly, &lt;em&gt;Ragnarok&lt;/em&gt; acknowledges what we&amp;rsquo;ve known from the beginning: superheroes are absurd and should be just as ridiculous as they are strong, smart, determined, and attractive. Play is woven into the fabric of the film, from Thor and Loki&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Get Help&amp;rdquo; fighting routine to Dr. Strange providing Thor a golden, bottomless beer fit for the Norse god (as promised to us at the end of the sorcerer&amp;rsquo;s own film). Even more serious topics, like Bannon and Hulk&amp;rsquo;s brain vs. brawn identity crisis and villain Hela&amp;rsquo;s description of executioners in Asgard are treated with a jesting lightness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ragnarok&lt;/em&gt; neatly sidesteps two pitfalls common to recent team-up superhero films: lack of screentime for its individual characters and weakening plot substance for the sake of comedy. In fact, some of the film&amp;rsquo;s most hysterical moments impressively include dialogue from three or more main characters while simultaneously advancing the story. When Thor, Bannon, and Valkerie discuss Loki&amp;rsquo;s past mischief while he remains chained but chuckling at their recounting of his past antics, the stratified ages of each character&amp;rsquo;s relationship with Loki shine: Thor and Loki&amp;rsquo;s escalating and ongoing brotherly conflict has existed as long as we&amp;rsquo;ve known them, Bannon last remembers Loki as an alien invader that needed smashing in the first Avengers, and Valkerie — while having as close as possible to a clean slate with Loki — generally mistrusts everyone. This lends itself perfectly to punchlines contrasting Bannon&amp;rsquo;s concerns with Loki&amp;rsquo;s murderous moods with Thor&amp;rsquo;s fond memories of being stabbed by Loki after thinking he was a snake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film&amp;rsquo;s more serious moments feel all the more poignant and starkly emotional against the backdrop of fun and games that dominate most of the dialogue. Watching the Hulk transform back into Bannon after being overcome with rage and grief on seeing Natasha is heartbreaking, and reminds us that the Hulk isn&amp;rsquo;t the only side of Bannon who carries the weight of his emotions. Heimdall inspires hope in an equally powerful way, and was an unmistakable Jesus figure to me. The way he sees all who are in need and fights for them — often alone in standing against evil and doing so without bravado or recognition — is exactly the kind of hero that inspires me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after yet another Marvel movie, what makes &lt;em&gt;Ragnarok&lt;/em&gt; stand out? We need look no further than the wonderfully quotable one-liners which litter its script, the well-developed and colorful cast of characters which populate its worlds, the perfected formula of self-aware superhero melodrama that guide its structure, and the underlying lessons of true heroism which are embodied by every main character, major and minor alike. If this is the direction Marvel is taking even a fraction of its future movies, I&amp;rsquo;m very excited to see what comes next.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overcooked</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-overcooked/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-overcooked/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a panda wielding a kitchen knife, desperately hacking away at as many onions as physically possible and subsequently littering the floor with chopped produce. The noise level in our living room steadily rises as my sister and I frantically shout back and forth at each other; the culinary space station we&amp;rsquo;ve been thrust into is about to rotate, and we&amp;rsquo;ll have a very narrow window before the station rotates again to ferry all the onions into another room where pots will transform them into delicious soups. But the discord is quickly joined by my brother, finding himself caught on the wrong side of an airlock, holding clean bowls for a set of soups that are nearly finished cooking. In a few moments, those soups will burn and set that section of the kitchen on fire; onions are bumped and kicked aside as my panda and my sister&amp;rsquo;s black bear accidentally dash into one another in our simultaneous attempts to get to the fire extinguisher. Orders are being missed, dirty dishes are piling up, soups are burning, tempers are fraying, and — most importantly — hilarity is ensuing. This is &lt;em&gt;Overcooked&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set with the task of avoiding certain apocalyptic doom caused by the appearance of a spaghetti monster that cannot be sated, players (controlling cartoon people and anthropomorphic animals) are sent back in time to hone their teamwork and culinary abilities. These cooperative teams of 1–4 players face challenges in cooking a variety of dishes, each introducing its own unique mechanics, in a variety of environments, each with its own hazards. Continuous failure to learn each level&amp;rsquo;s unspoken rules and strategies quickly is more often a source of comedy than of frustration, and any attempts to rely on a comfort strategy are almost always usurped by little surprises to further refine your growing culinary expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most part, each level is fairly straightforward: obtain ingredients, chop them, assemble them into dishes, cook those dishes, plate them, serve them, and literally rinse and repeat by washing the dirty plates when they&amp;rsquo;re returned. The faster dishes are served, the more money they&amp;rsquo;re worth, and a score of 1 (passing) to 3 (perfect) stars can be scored on each level depending on the total money earned. The numerous ways each stage of preparation overlaps with the others offers more than enough material for flustering and amusing kitchen accidents, but it&amp;rsquo;s the small mechanics tweaks and zany interactions between the players and their environment that keep the already incredible core experience fresh throughout the course of the game. Mishaps abound, such as accidentally throwing away clean dishes instead of handing them to another player or slipping off an iceberg holding a finished pizza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the game can be played alone (wherein a single player controls multiple avatars and switches between them), &lt;em&gt;Overcooked&lt;/em&gt;&amp;lsquo;s hilarity of mistakes (and mistakes on top of mistakes) combined with the thrill of (eventual) success is best experienced with friends. In an age where couch co-op is largely ignored in the wake of big screen multiplayer titles, &lt;em&gt;Overcooked&lt;/em&gt; not only succeeds in creating a satisfying co-op experience but adds innovative elements beyond the usual cooking game. If &lt;em&gt;Overcooked&lt;/em&gt; were a meal, then Ghost Town Games has prepared us something truly wonderful and family-style; my compliments to the chefs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
