<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>creative | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/categories/creative/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/categories/creative/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>creative</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 09:15:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/images/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>creative</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/categories/creative/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Three Academics: A Joke</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/post/the-three-academics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 09:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/post/the-three-academics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mathematicians really care about correctness. We believe unspoken assumptions are dangerous. We think vague language is confusing, and saying more or less than we mean is grounds for misunderstanding. We want terms to be clearly defined, and for points to follow logically, like links in an unbreakable chain of truth. But sometimes people say things that are completely reasonable and yet we still feel the need to set them straight:&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/post/the-three-academics/the-three-academics-lowres_huc2345e23d7c9b85a48da5ce8d8476a68_168428_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/post/the-three-academics/the-three-academics-lowres_huc2345e23d7c9b85a48da5ce8d8476a68_168428_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;850&#34; height=&#34;1100&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first contribution to the world of webcomics, a medium I&amp;rsquo;ve long admired for being able to deliver witty, weird reflections on life in simple packages. Giving credit where it&amp;rsquo;s due, this &amp;ldquo;joke&amp;rdquo; is adapted from 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1618.The_Curious_Incident_of_the_Dog_in_the_Night_Time&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Curious Case of the Dog in the Night-Time&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Haddon and the art style takes after 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/poorlydrawnlines/?hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;poorlydrawnlines&lt;/a&gt; by Reza Farazmand. In living out 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.alabasterco.com/blogs/articles/all-that-is-made&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;generous making&lt;/a&gt;, this comic is available as a high resolution &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/files/the-three-academics-highres.png&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PNG&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/files/the-three-academics.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; for you to use as you&amp;rsquo;d like. (Just keep my authorship in the corner intact, please!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, to the economists out there: if you&amp;rsquo;ve got any good roasts of mathematicians, I&amp;rsquo;m all ears.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oh, the Places You&#39;ll Go</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/post/oh-the-places-youll-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 12:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/post/oh-the-places-youll-go/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student, I get to travel quite a bit. In just the last two years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been to Atlanta (a few times, once as a visiting researcher to GaTech for 3 months), Austin, Vienna, Dagstuhl, and — most recently — Tokyo. I get to meet interesting researchers on every trip, whether it be during a conference coffee break (where &amp;ldquo;meeting&amp;rdquo; people occasionally feels like getting interrogated about research) or by running into each other while meandering through a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.japan-guide.com/e/e3034_001.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;national park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vyza5tbx-qc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These trips are largely work. I listen to talks on the latest research and imagine ways to connect them to my own. I introduce myself to more senior researchers (usually hesitantly) in the hopes that they&amp;rsquo;ll remember who I am once they&amp;rsquo;re through answering my questions. I stay up way too late the night before my talk polishing my slides to (what I hope is) perfection. I scribble all over whiteboards, drawing (mostly) intelligible pictures when working out new ideas with collaborators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Need to update &amp;ldquo;slides&amp;rdquo; with a link to the talk I gave at WSSR.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then there&amp;rsquo;s the beauty of getting to go to new places &lt;em&gt;because I have to&lt;/em&gt;. As an introvert and someone who&amp;rsquo;s pretty happy being in one place, travel is definitely not an itch I need to scratch (to me, &amp;ldquo;wanderlust&amp;rdquo; often feels like a made up word fellow Millennials use to describe the need for jealousy-inducing Instagram content). But my PhD has helped me learn that there&amp;rsquo;s a lot out there to see and understand, and somehow the difference and uncertainty and novelty of it all makes me feel hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, until we meet again, Tokyo.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
