<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>science | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/science/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>science</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jul 2021 12:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/media/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>science</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/science/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Outer Wilds</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-outer-wilds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jul 2021 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-outer-wilds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Against the backdrop of a diorama solar system in a diorama universe, &lt;em&gt;Outer Wilds&lt;/em&gt; plunges forward into an ambitious adventure of wonder and exploration.
You play as the sixth member of your species to venture out into space — and the first to do so with a translation device for the language of the Nomai, an ancient species that mysteriously disappeared a long time ago.
Remnants of their civilization are scattered all around your solar system, like bread crumbs in a nonlinear trail, inviting you into their mystery.
What were the Nomai doing?
Where did they go?
What&amp;rsquo;s it all for?&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /review/videogame-outer-wilds/nomaischematics_hu850032374c8e22d7c3a6ee5181beb27f_1853793_8795a9b84ee65d8c63f55a17d07dad0a.png 400w,
               /review/videogame-outer-wilds/nomaischematics_hu850032374c8e22d7c3a6ee5181beb27f_1853793_eab8e4662d89d5fec492cf03b31eba11.png 760w,
               /review/videogame-outer-wilds/nomaischematics_hu850032374c8e22d7c3a6ee5181beb27f_1853793_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-outer-wilds/nomaischematics_hu850032374c8e22d7c3a6ee5181beb27f_1853793_8795a9b84ee65d8c63f55a17d07dad0a.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enthusiastically recommend &lt;em&gt;Outer Wilds&lt;/em&gt; to anyone who will listen; it&amp;rsquo;s a resounding 10/10.
I love the world and its inhabitants, and their ideals to explore and to understand.
The music frequently brings me to a very emotional place (more on that in a moment).
But this game&amp;rsquo;s best quality is its unique ability to engage players at the intersection of imagination and discovery: learning new information pushes you to form new questions, which in turn makes you seek new answers, and then the cycle repeats.
The nonlinear narrative supports your curiosity in whatever direction you decide to go; there are no artificial checkpoints or cutscenes pushing you towards a specific experience.
The way you engage with this world is your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Outer Wilds&lt;/em&gt; is surprisingly capable at blending the whimsy and brutality of space exploration.
Your spaceship is made of wood, of all things, and yet is often your only life support in the cold void of space.
Plummeting into a black hole is surprisingly non-lethal, but what awaits on the other side is nevertheless crushingly isolating.
Extremely bizarre things happen on a regular basis — like getting launched from a planet into low orbit only to crash back down — but manage to feel more bemusing than terrifying.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /review/videogame-outer-wilds/sunandembertwin_hu764ad56c509280e7a5ecd0d1fc05eb09_2114230_a8afe67fe00801f02d0ff55b479a278c.png 400w,
               /review/videogame-outer-wilds/sunandembertwin_hu764ad56c509280e7a5ecd0d1fc05eb09_2114230_51fc0110492a35c9f5a77dc2edef0c9e.png 760w,
               /review/videogame-outer-wilds/sunandembertwin_hu764ad56c509280e7a5ecd0d1fc05eb09_2114230_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-outer-wilds/sunandembertwin_hu764ad56c509280e7a5ecd0d1fc05eb09_2114230_a8afe67fe00801f02d0ff55b479a278c.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the music!
Funnily enough, when I fired up &lt;em&gt;Outer Wilds&lt;/em&gt; for the first time, I didn&amp;rsquo;t make it past the main menu.
I was captivated by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://soundcloud.com/andrewprahlow/main-title&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;title track&lt;/a&gt;.
As I watched the little campfire come to life, the theme&amp;rsquo;s dueling banjos sang optimism and hope into the deep black of space.
The composer, Andrew Prahlow, layers a bright foreground he recorded just before development wrapped with a background that he&amp;rsquo;d recorded &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/LbY0mBXKKT0?t=2411&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;seven years prior&lt;/a&gt; — a detail that&amp;rsquo;s both beyond incredible and very difficult to appreciate without having first finished the game.
Suffice it to say, this is my favorite game soundtrack, and I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to many.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /review/videogame-outer-wilds/opening_hue4e580f276037637a8acdceda0b8789c_2447327_79503bc24e7b47e8aa5fd3e0b1fc8e85.png 400w,
               /review/videogame-outer-wilds/opening_hue4e580f276037637a8acdceda0b8789c_2447327_ae0545433c5c675d0e15562a2e8e95ac.png 760w,
               /review/videogame-outer-wilds/opening_hue4e580f276037637a8acdceda0b8789c_2447327_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-outer-wilds/opening_hue4e580f276037637a8acdceda0b8789c_2447327_79503bc24e7b47e8aa5fd3e0b1fc8e85.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, &lt;em&gt;Outer Wilds&lt;/em&gt; achieves a mark of masterclass sci-fi, wrapping the vast happenings of the universe into a story that is deeply personal.
It sets us off asking questions about physics and ancient anthropology but, along the way, teaches us to ask questions of ourselves.
How could we be more open-handed and filled with wonder, like the Nomai?
What do we do with the memories of people and experiences long gone?
How can we live bravely in the face of a constantly uncertain future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s tempting to linger in this moment, while every possibility still exists.
But unless they are collapsed by an observer, they will never be more than possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Story of More</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/book-the-story-of-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 13:52:54 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/book-the-story-of-more/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Climate change has become one of many sources of existential dread that I share with my generation, albeit one that I was slow to understand. Growing up in a conservative evangelical context, global warming was right up there with evolution in terms of science that was treated as if it contested the nature of God, his creation, and humanity&amp;rsquo;s place within it. Combined with teachers that were shy about the realities of our earth&amp;rsquo;s sickness and our hand in its decay, our plight was fuzzy to me, at best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet activism and justice (social, environmental, political) are in the water now — albeit often diluted and consumed in the form of social media. The United States&#39; withdrawal from the Paris Agreement was another Trump decision to throw on the pile of his wrongdoings. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://marchforscience.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;March for Science&lt;/a&gt; is now a three-year-old movement to use science for the common good and spur change. Natural disasters are now frequently linked to &amp;ldquo;weirding weather.&amp;rdquo; And yet, while I know climate change denial is an ostrich&amp;rsquo;s approach to problem solving, my knowledge on what the Paris Agreement says, what the March for Science marches for, or the cause-and-effect behind why the weather is now weird is embarrassingly limited. I&amp;rsquo;ve been drawing lines in the sand about &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;bad&amp;rdquo; approaches to our natural world without real knowledge, which is a lousy and ineffective place to try and enact change from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope Jahren&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Story of More&lt;/em&gt; is a wonderful primer on our natural history and how we got ourselves into the mess we&amp;rsquo;re in. By seamlessly weaving chatty stories about growing up in the American Midwest with no-nonsense, no-jargon statistics, Hope expertly guides us through Climate Science 101 less like a lecturing professor (though she is that) and more like a  wise and smart friend. For nearly the entire book, she simply presents her findings without bias or interpretation — with a brief break in character to rant about how much she hates cars — seemingly trusting that we can wrestle with the implications ourselves. She shows us that it all boils down to some basic fundamentals: how many of us there are, the food we eat and where it comes from, the energy we use and how we produce it, and, finally, how all of that affects the natural world we live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of scaring the public for the sake of scaring it scares me&amp;hellip; People don&amp;rsquo;t make good decisions out of fear, history seems to have shown, and at least some of the time, people who are afraid are also prone to doing nothing&amp;hellip; My own goal is to inform you, not to scare you, because teaching has taught me to know and respect the difference. I&amp;rsquo;ve found that fear makes us turn away from the issue whereas information draws us in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;em&gt;The Story of More&lt;/em&gt;, pages 139–140.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Story of More&lt;/em&gt; is the story of our relentless pursuit of &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; food, &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; energy, &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; variety, &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; transportation, &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; possessions, &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; comfort. Conservation was discarded in favor of efficiency; instead of targeting &amp;ldquo;more for less&amp;rdquo;, we pursued &amp;ldquo;much more for more&amp;rdquo;. This mix of scientific findings and historical narrative is powerful and helped me understand modern first-world life in new ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the appendix entitled &amp;ldquo;The Story of Less,&amp;rdquo; Hope offers some reflection questions on how we each can &lt;em&gt;use less and share more&lt;/em&gt;. There are no cut and dry answers (and, as it turns out, there are more problems than any one of us could solve alone), but she provides a framework that gave me clarity beyond the behavior and tone matching of today&amp;rsquo;s armchair activism. I&amp;rsquo;m very thankful for her voice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
