<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>dynamic-networks | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/dynamic-networks/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/dynamic-networks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>dynamic-networks</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/media/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>dynamic-networks</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/dynamic-networks/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Self-Organization in Anonymous Dynamic Networks</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/project/dynamic-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/project/dynamic-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Distributed computing theory has matured well beyond its original inspiration of dedicated computers linked together in static networks for message passing and file sharing.
A key theme across modern applications of distributed computing is the impact of &lt;em&gt;dynamics&lt;/em&gt;, or frequent changes in the system&amp;rsquo;s members or the connections among them.
This paradigm shift has enabled distributed computing to innovate both within computer science—e.g., in the construction of self-stabilizing overlay networks—and beyond the realm of engineering in, e.g., economics, biology, neurology, and active matter physics.
Motivated by these domains where individuals often have limited to no explicit computational power, we study the &lt;em&gt;algorithmic theory of dynamic networks&lt;/em&gt; where nodes are &lt;em&gt;anonymous&lt;/em&gt; (lacking unique identifiers), have &lt;em&gt;sublogarithmic memory&lt;/em&gt; (insufficient for computing identifiers), and communicate via &lt;em&gt;message passing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are specifically interested in &lt;em&gt;asynchronous concurrency&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;adaptive self-organization&lt;/em&gt;.
In studying asynchronous concurrency, we challenge the literature&amp;rsquo;s ubiquitous simplifying assumption that computation and network dynamics remain separated in time, instead designing algorithms that achieve their desired goals in spite of concurrent topological changes.
With adaptive self-organization, we initiate the study of an orthogonal type of dynamics, &lt;em&gt;time-varying system tasks&lt;/em&gt;, which require algorithms to simultaneously adapt to the environment and achieve self-stabilization.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local Mutual Exclusion for Dynamic, Anonymous, Bounded Memory Message Passing Systems</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/publication/daymude2022-localmutual/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/publication/daymude2022-localmutual/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Local Mutual Exclusion for Dynamic, Anonymous, Bounded Memory Message Passing Systems</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/event/2022sand-localmutual/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 17:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/event/2022sand-localmutual/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
