<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>atmospheric-horror | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/atmospheric-horror/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/atmospheric-horror/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>atmospheric-horror</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 19:08:32 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/media/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>atmospheric-horror</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/atmospheric-horror/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Control</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 19:08:32 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-control/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Control&lt;/em&gt; exerts full mastery over videogames as a unique narrative form, blending motion-capture acting performances, live-action filmed skits and monologues, puppet shows, radio programs, rock albums, short stories, technical documentation, a whole slew of homages to other videogame genres, and — of course — shooting weird shit that needs to be shot.
While not a must, &lt;em&gt;Control&lt;/em&gt; and its Oldest House are best experienced in the progressive revelations and immersive weirdness so carefully crafted by its developers.
The remainder of this review may contain atmospheric and thematic spoilers.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /review/videogame-control/darlinglab_hu471d3b84ad02b33ff440bd4b1443ac0c_13269229_4a4e2ded0cf0e2069c1d4191dec0dcb3.png 400w,
               /review/videogame-control/darlinglab_hu471d3b84ad02b33ff440bd4b1443ac0c_13269229_da53c9220be5e207c05b6876b4e21d25.png 760w,
               /review/videogame-control/darlinglab_hu471d3b84ad02b33ff440bd4b1443ac0c_13269229_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-control/darlinglab_hu471d3b84ad02b33ff440bd4b1443ac0c_13269229_4a4e2ded0cf0e2069c1d4191dec0dcb3.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Control&lt;/em&gt; should be remembered, if not for any of its other solid qualities, as a milestone in storytelling with the gaming medium.
It&amp;rsquo;s one thing to have high quality voice acting and motion capture — especially for facial expressions — so that your game characters can converse more naturally than, say, Siri.
It&amp;rsquo;s another thing entirely to film talented actors and put that footage in the game, a technique Remedy continues here from their past work in &lt;em&gt;Quantum Break&lt;/em&gt; and, to a lesser extent, &lt;em&gt;Alan Wake&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Bright Falls&lt;/em&gt;.
The narrative tricks needed to pull this off (namely, the Hotline and littering the Oldest House with instructional films and research updates) are clever.
Weaving tie-ins between those short films and the mass of mixed-medium work throughout the rest of the game is impressive.
But slowly coming to grips with the collective efforts of directors, writers, actors, visual artists, programmers, managers, and the many, many others involved in developing a game of this caliber is staggering.
To experience artistry that feels genuinely new is a deep joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesse Faden (Courtney Hope), our protagonist, is solid ground in the physically and metaphorically shifting strangeness of the Oldest House.
We get to watch the depth of her inner worries and assessments balance with her do-what-we-came-to-do attitude to round out a reasonably believable human being.
She&amp;rsquo;s relational, witty, and exceptionally brave: unlike me, she does not freak out when ambushed by shrieking resonance zombies.
The player may be holding the controller, but this is Jesse&amp;rsquo;s story and she is in control.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /review/videogame-control/deadletters_hu22768126cfc898da6df58e5b94ef368d_9677457_9c3fa6311828fe013d8ed836b5a39268.png 400w,
               /review/videogame-control/deadletters_hu22768126cfc898da6df58e5b94ef368d_9677457_1bb8423f2034d09922e30568d51f7d8f.png 760w,
               /review/videogame-control/deadletters_hu22768126cfc898da6df58e5b94ef368d_9677457_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-control/deadletters_hu22768126cfc898da6df58e5b94ef368d_9677457_9c3fa6311828fe013d8ed836b5a39268.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Control, aside from being the literal name of the game, is a central theme under exploration.
What does it mean to have control?
Who had it before and who has it now?
What do you do with control when it&amp;rsquo;s yours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Power, the story posits, is not the same as control.
Control is more elusive.
It requires understanding, trust, and genuine leadership — qualities that Jesse&amp;rsquo;s predecessors Northmoor and Trench traded away in their pursuit of, ironically, control.
But instead of probing this theme more deeply (for example, asking whether control itself is just an illusory sense of security), the game&amp;rsquo;s conclusion is satisfied with replacing entrenched, toxic leaders with Jesse and other critically thinking young people and calling it a day.
The &lt;em&gt;Foundation&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;AWE&lt;/em&gt; DLCs do a little more work in this direction, but fall short of staking out a thoughtful value claim to complement the robust narrative creativity.
I&amp;rsquo;d hoped for more.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /review/videogame-control/soundroom_hu97ea86f693491786ffd8c82ceb90bfa2_14313455_b01adf5f5641e14093f72b18d752b934.png 400w,
               /review/videogame-control/soundroom_hu97ea86f693491786ffd8c82ceb90bfa2_14313455_5f36b80ce19d5f562fb1428ecb61f81d.png 760w,
               /review/videogame-control/soundroom_hu97ea86f693491786ffd8c82ceb90bfa2_14313455_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-control/soundroom_hu97ea86f693491786ffd8c82ceb90bfa2_14313455_b01adf5f5641e14093f72b18d752b934.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amidst all this focus on artistry, narrative, and hopes for philosophy, it&amp;rsquo;s still worth mentioning that the gunplay and paranatural combat abilities feel great.
Returning to other games after being Jesse Faden is markedly disappointing.
Said another way, you know how exhilarating the combat in &lt;em&gt;Control&lt;/em&gt; is going to be from the first moment you accidentally bump into a table and the physics engine sends it flying into a wall, papers thrust into the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited to know the talented folks at Remedy are already working on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.polygon.com/22556019/control-sequel-multiplayer-spinoff-pc-xbox-ps5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;new stories&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;Control&lt;/em&gt; universe, and for what other developers and artists this quality of videogame storytelling might inspire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bugs&#34;&gt;Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s minor, but there was an occasional issue where the floor would just&amp;hellip; disappear.
At first I thought this was a thing the Oldest House did; then after an extended period of confusion I realized some textures just weren&amp;rsquo;t loading.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /review/videogame-control/floorbug_hu2a4f98ea48d4cfd72de22c655851d2d9_11707162_9c8b7863356240629bff972d02fecc59.png 400w,
               /review/videogame-control/floorbug_hu2a4f98ea48d4cfd72de22c655851d2d9_11707162_66b151ae56ebe47b37dc6bef219f8ac8.png 760w,
               /review/videogame-control/floorbug_hu2a4f98ea48d4cfd72de22c655851d2d9_11707162_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-control/floorbug_hu2a4f98ea48d4cfd72de22c655851d2d9_11707162_9c8b7863356240629bff972d02fecc59.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, while not a bug, I&amp;rsquo;m highly skeptical of an office building with lids on their public toilets.
Like.
Who does this?
The Federal Bureau of Control, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /review/videogame-control/toilets_hu51f52b82679017d68d67f516aa5fab5d_12345706_9eb1b276bfb13d1616aa2efd3e44fa05.png 400w,
               /review/videogame-control/toilets_hu51f52b82679017d68d67f516aa5fab5d_12345706_6c5133d8fe4f0ed579abd31ef949464b.png 760w,
               /review/videogame-control/toilets_hu51f52b82679017d68d67f516aa5fab5d_12345706_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-control/toilets_hu51f52b82679017d68d67f516aa5fab5d_12345706_9eb1b276bfb13d1616aa2efd3e44fa05.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We Were Here</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-we-were-here/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-we-were-here/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this two-player, cooperative, escape-the-room-like adventure, players take the roles of the Librarian and the Explorer. The two begin the game stranded in an unspecified snowy region, and upon discovering and entering a foreboding castle, they are knocked out and placed in separate rooms, connected only by a pair of walkie-talkies. The Librarian is primarily responsible for supplying information to the Explorer, who in turn navigates deadly traps and dimly lit mazes to reach new areas. By piecing together visual clues from both players&#39; environments, puzzles are solved cooperatively, opening doors to new challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a free-to-play game, this was a surprisingly enjoyable and well-constructed experience (albeit a relatively short one, with an imperfect run taking roughly two hours). The crux of the gameplay rests on using voice-only communication to navigate inherently visual puzzles, which are fairly high-quality. Each puzzle balances complexity with difficulty in a pleasing way, and remains sufficiently independent of the rest, ensuring that each sequence is fresh and surprising. Even so, the overall experience was cohesive, rewarding attention to detail even when the details weren&amp;rsquo;t immediately relevant. Making the roles unique gives the game replay value as well; even though both players know the puzzle solutions after one successful run, switching roles gives a satisfying &amp;ldquo;ah, that&amp;rsquo;s what you were confused about!&amp;rdquo; kind of feeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graphics are lacking in polish, but this is hardly a complaint given the game is free. In some senses, the lower quality textures add to the experience; I don&amp;rsquo;t really like horror games, but the use of creepy atmospheric elements and the ever-present sense that my partner was in danger was enough to create the right amount of suspense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My real complaints are lodged against the bugs we encountered in our play-through, which (as of Update Five) required my Explorer to kill himself so we could restart from the checkpoint. This sort of broke the feeling of the overall experience, as death became a necessary means to an end instead of something worth fearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, as a matter of opinion and not of critique, I wonder if the story could have offered any more resolution than what was hinted at in the final theatre sequence. Who was the shadowy figure that placed us here? What drives it to such strange games of mind-over-matter? And what does it want with the one left behind?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bugs&#34;&gt;Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Update Five, the introductory video has audio buffering issues. The chess puzzle has a couple bugs: the librarian often drops the film reel for no reason, and it is possible to get the film reel to play its spinning animation on the table itself if the Explorer applies the power too early.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
