<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>adventure | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/adventure/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/adventure/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>adventure</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 12:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/images/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>adventure</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/adventure/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Batman: Arkham City</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-batman-arkham-city/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-batman-arkham-city/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I played &lt;em&gt;Arkham Asylum&lt;/em&gt; back in summer of 2015, so it somehow seems fitting for this much busier stage of my life that it took me four years to play the sequel. That being said, the gap I&amp;rsquo;ve taken from the &lt;em&gt;Batman: Arkham&lt;/em&gt; series may ultimately have been to my benefit, given just how similar &lt;em&gt;Arkham City&lt;/em&gt; feels to &lt;em&gt;Arkham Asylum&lt;/em&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;re still beating the crap out of every other living character in the game (who all seem inexplicably hostile towards us on sight), we&amp;rsquo;re still uncovering a diabolical plot that features an all-star cast of Batman villains, and we&amp;rsquo;re still tracking down every Riddler secret using every piece of WayneTech we can get our hands on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, all of it is &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;. Very few superhero games, especially those being made back in the early 2010s, can hold a candle to the experience that &lt;em&gt;Arkham City&lt;/em&gt; provides. From gliding and grappling through the city to using detective mode to solve crimes, every moment feels like an authentic, exhilarating experience of donning the cape and cowl of the Dark Knight. Catwoman, Robin, and Nightwing are also playable characters for smaller segments, each with their own exciting gadgets and play styles. A huge amount of the game&amp;rsquo;s success can be credited to the immersive open-world of &lt;em&gt;Arkham City&lt;/em&gt;, greatly improving over the labyrinth Metroidvania-like level design of &lt;em&gt;Arkham Asylum&lt;/em&gt;. Adding a mix of outdoor and indoor locations to the game adds further opportunities for the mechanics and side missions to enrich the overall experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this brings me to a point of &lt;em&gt;Arkham City&lt;/em&gt; I was surprised by, and one that I would have only picked up on now, in 2019. Thanks to the open-world design, we get a lot of radio chatter from various inmates and characters to make the solo experience feel more alive. Most of what they say is fine but forgettable, like &amp;ldquo;I wonder what&amp;rsquo;s on TV right now,&amp;rdquo; or self-dating to an era where Facebook was still a novelty: &amp;ldquo;How am I supposed to update my status? &amp;hellip;Oh yeah, I&amp;rsquo;m still stuck here in this stinking prison.&amp;rdquo; But a lot of it hints at something much more sinister, not originating from the inmates themselves, but from their experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, the plot of the game is that Prof. Hugo Strange gets Gotham City to agree to a pretty bonkers plan wherein they wall off a huge part of the city, throw all the inmates and supervillains from Arkham Asylum inside, and seal it shut. Strange likes this because he gets to &amp;ldquo;study&amp;rdquo; the criminally insane (for the good of science, I&amp;rsquo;m sure), and because the prison is a perfect way of making sure anyone who knows the truth of his nefarious purposes (like Bruce Wayne) are never heard from again. But in an age where we&amp;rsquo;re talking a lot more about racial discrimination, police brutality, and other failures of our criminal justice system, you start to wonder why in the world Batman feels the need to be inside this prison, beating the pulp out of everyone he sees. A decent number of inmates will yell &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s Batman doing here?&amp;rdquo; when you start a fight. Others get picked up by your police scanner: &amp;ldquo;Why&amp;rsquo;s Batman in here anyway, aren&amp;rsquo;t we already locked up?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that a lot of these inmates are bad people, especially the more ruthless ones who work closely with the big bads (Penguin, Two-Face, Joker, etc.). But my guess is that a lot of the inmates joined up with some villain&amp;rsquo;s faction just so they had food to eat, or so they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t get killed in the streets. And while I know Batman will never be compassionate, I wonder if he couldn&amp;rsquo;t be just a bit more conscientious. Otherwise, I worry that Joker&amp;rsquo;s right when he says Batman belongs inside with the rest of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bugs&#34;&gt;Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game would occasionally crash with some pretty unreadable error messages, but was otherwise flawless.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Phantom Tollbooth</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/book-the-phantom-tollbooth/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/book-the-phantom-tollbooth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Phantom Tollbooth&lt;/em&gt; is a fable in every chapter, clever wit in every paragraph, and careful thought in every sentence. It is both a treatise on critical thinking and a tender story of a young boy&amp;rsquo;s adventure. It is just as much an epic struggle between Wisdom and Ignorance as it is a playful comedy where the first character to cry is a watchdog named Tock lamenting the fact that he goes &lt;em&gt;ticktickticktick&lt;/em&gt; while his brother Tick goes &lt;em&gt;tocktocktocktock&lt;/em&gt;. Perhaps most importantly, its excellence is a testament to the fruits of curious wonder and deep wisdom, two values that its fantastical characters try very hard to get Milo — the protagonist — to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every word is an absolute joy to read. Norton Juster achieves the kind of simplicity that comes at the cost of both knowing what exactly one wants to write and cutting away all superfluous material that does not achieve that goal. The entire novel is written in everyday prose fitting for a bedtime story, and yet contains layers of subtlety that should give the reading adult pause. Juster masterfully mixes serious lessons (that must not be obvious even to many adults, seeing how our world is) with hysterical moments of relief, all in a stream of whimsical adventure. Take, for example, the following scene:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except for these, and the big brass cannon being pulled along behind, they all looked very much like the residents of any other small valley to which you&amp;rsquo;ve never been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;em&gt;The Phantom Tollbooth&lt;/em&gt;, page 146.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paradox, absurdity, and humor, all wrapped into such a simple little description. Or take, for example, an unabashed jab Juster takes at the Humbug:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After demonstrating that there was nothing up his sleeves, in his hat, or behind his back, [the Mathemagician] wrote quickly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 + 9 – 2 x 16 + 1 ÷ 3 x 6 – 67 + 8 x 2 – 3 + 26 – 1 ÷ 34 + 3 ÷ 7 + 2 – 5 =&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then he looked up expectantly.
“Seventeen!” The Humbug shouted, who always managed to be the first with the wrong answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;em&gt;The Phantom Tollbooth&lt;/em&gt;, page 188.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pages of this book are riddled with such perfect moments as these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure that many compelling essays have been (or could be) written on the many social tendencies &lt;em&gt;The Phantom Tollbooth&lt;/em&gt; chases after with the sharpest wit — getting lost in trivial tasks, becoming an arrogant and condescending specialist, or being too afraid to have your own thoughts, for example — but it suffices to say that &lt;em&gt;The Phantom Tollbooth&lt;/em&gt; gives a looking glass into how our own world has banished its Rhyme and Reason. It is relevant even today, nearly 60 years after its original publication. But unlike the dystopias of its time, &lt;em&gt;The Phantom Tollbooth&lt;/em&gt; is permeated with hope. And with what better weapon can one burn back the darkness?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And remember also,” added the Princess of Sweet Rhyme, “that many places you would like to see are just off the map and many things you want to know are just out of sight or a little beyond your reach. But someday you&amp;rsquo;ll reach them all, for what you learn today, for no reason at all, will help you discover all the wonderful secrets of tomorrow.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;em&gt;The Phantom Tollbooth&lt;/em&gt;, page 234.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Isle of Dogs</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/movie-isle-of-dogs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jun 2018 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/movie-isle-of-dogs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Isle of Dogs&lt;/em&gt;, Wes Anderson brings all the style, heart, and wit of &lt;em&gt;Fantastic Mr. Fox (2009)&lt;/em&gt; to a story of his own. This story is told by means of a prologue and four (very clearly labeled) acts following a young boy and a pack of dogs as they struggle against a geopolitical scheme to try and rid their home city of its canine friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Isle of Dogs&lt;/em&gt; plays with language extensively, and uses the quirks of its world to its advantage. Dog barks are &amp;ldquo;translated&amp;rdquo; into English for the viewer&amp;rsquo;s pleasure, while the humans speak their native tongue (Japanese, occasionally translated by a literal translator). There&amp;rsquo;s low-hanging fruit, like when the lead dog Chief (Bryan Cranston) tells another to pass on a message to a &amp;ldquo;bitch you&amp;rsquo;ll find there&amp;rdquo;, as well as light social commentary, like when Chief asks to see showdog Nutmeg&amp;rsquo;s (Scarlett Johansson) &amp;ldquo;tricks&amp;rdquo; but she refuses, or when Chief tries to reckon with his own nature and violent responses (&amp;ldquo;I bite, but I don&amp;rsquo;t know why.&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as important as dog-to-dog and human-to-human dialogue is in furthering plot points and poking fun at the absurdity of the film, some of the most profound moments occur in the space between humans and their best friends, where actions and emotions establish connections where words cannot. In particular, watching the relationships between Atari (Koyu Rankin) and the main pack of dogs unfold is satisfying, endearing, and at times hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The winsome, charming world of tactile materials in stop-motion style doesn&amp;rsquo;t bar the film from diving into more gruesome scenes, like killing live sea creatures to prepare sushi or performing a kidney surgery. It also gives a platform to build up caricatures of relevant issues, like political leaders ignoring scientific findings, youth protesting against the powers at be, and marginalized populations being abused and mistreated for the betterment of the majority. That being said, this is a Wes Anderson film, so it certainly comes complete with its 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rollingstone.com/movies/movie-news/how-do-you-solve-a-problem-like-isle-of-dogs-204452/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;problematic blind spots&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This film was thoroughly enjoyable and another wonderful addition to the Anderson filmography. Smart, touching, beautiful, and odd, it seems to both exist in another world and yet feel deeply personal, a whimsical analogy to a human&amp;rsquo;s relationship with our four-legged friends.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
