<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>space | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/space/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/space/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>space</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2021 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 12:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/images/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>space</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tags/space/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Outer Worlds</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-the-outer-worlds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-the-outer-worlds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt; promised to let you, &amp;ldquo;the unknown variable,&amp;rdquo; truly role-play in the wild world of Halycon. Want to be the hero and save the world? Sure, who doesn&amp;rsquo;t? Want to steer your jaded friends towards self-awareness and hope? Just might work. Want to murder everyone on sight, including major companions and story-critical characters? Have a great time, you monster. Streamers have basically tried it all, and the game does indeed deliver. I particularly enjoyed embodying some kind of scientist/intellectual with an aversion for violence and a deep need to screw some corporate tools over.&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-the-outer-worlds/edgewaternight_hua95115548d781dc70255b1e6927bd015_2440629_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-the-outer-worlds/edgewaternight_hua95115548d781dc70255b1e6927bd015_2440629_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1920&#34; height=&#34;1080&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What most impressed me was the world building packed into this tight, 40-ish hour experience. Every character looks different, has their own believable personality, and acts based on real fears and hopes. Most remember past encounters with you and have whole conversations scripted for the late-game, even when they&amp;rsquo;re just &amp;ldquo;extras&amp;rdquo; that have nothing to do with the ongoing story. Your companions are the best examples of the developers&amp;rsquo; care and attention to detail: one companion develops a love interest and wants to grab drinks with you to get your thoughts — this leads to a tipsy bar visit where you get to give dating advice. Other characters are working through past hurts and losses that shape who they are in the current narrative. It all feels very &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt;, and that aspect alone (against the stark contrast of the very inhumane slave-like colony townships) is enough to pull you into the first several hours of gameplay and give gravity to the difficult choices you have to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The characters made me savor conversations, walking up to every NPC just to make sure I wasn&amp;rsquo;t missing personal backstories or historical context. I found myself imagining those who would be unjustly punished for my decisions to stir up trouble, or who I could win over by showing some semblance of kindness. The world felt open and full of possibility, while harboring many situations with hidden consequences.&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-the-outer-worlds/lavaflows_hu69c586f845e63269f64449ba8b24ebf9_2669693_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-the-outer-worlds/lavaflows_hu69c586f845e63269f64449ba8b24ebf9_2669693_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1920&#34; height=&#34;1080&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, some of this delightful, game-outside-the-game enchantment faded when I realized a very simple reality: what felt like a cliff of consequence was really just a short ledge, and every mistake I made could usually be solved by shooting my way through. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily the only solution (for example, I appreciated the go-and-kill quests that offered diplomacy as a non-violent alternative), but violence was often the path of least resistance. I slowly deteriorated from a hero who respected life — killing only when just or necessary — to a skilled mercenary with a vague conscience who also happened to enjoy conversation. The magic wasn&amp;rsquo;t there in the same way after that reality set in.&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-the-outer-worlds/scylla_hu224bb35c97e260bf23d205f44c29c329_2845510_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-the-outer-worlds/scylla_hu224bb35c97e260bf23d205f44c29c329_2845510_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1920&#34; height=&#34;1080&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this is what &lt;em&gt;The Outer Worlds&lt;/em&gt; had promised all along: that there would be many paths that one could fully explore, even if not all of are equally satisfying. It&amp;rsquo;s less that you live with your choices and more that your choices happen to the game, forcing it to bend and twist around you. And in that way, it really is a wonderful role-playing experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bugs&#34;&gt;Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I had a syncing issue with save files between different Xbox consoles, but this may have been a fluke.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was one view on Monarch where the environment didn&amp;rsquo;t render correctly, and whole stone structures seemed to disappear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was awarded one achievement (&amp;ldquo;Pirate Radio&amp;rdquo;) out of the blue, unsure what exactly I did to get it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sputnik Eyes</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-sputnik-eyes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2016 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-sputnik-eyes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sputnik Eyes&lt;/em&gt; is a puzzle game adorned with a playful atmosphere in which you&amp;rsquo;re tasked with guiding exploratory colored robots to matching color positions in order to discover new planets. The aesthetic is greatly inspired by space exploration and the mathematical field of graph theory, which delivers enjoyable mechanics for mathy logic puzzles in minimalist artwork and easily understood controls. The UI is full of adorable artwork, reminiscent of cartoon depictions of outer space that might decorate a child&amp;rsquo;s bedroom. The soundtrack is similarly dreamy, leveraging a handful of light, instrumental electronic songs on rotation to keep any one from becoming overplayed.&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-sputnik-eyes/level_hu4b4ff64bd98f5c51248ec04c7cd85531_222619_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-sputnik-eyes/level_hu4b4ff64bd98f5c51248ec04c7cd85531_222619_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;1136&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the levels vary in the layout of finishing positions and the number of robots, gameplay does have the potential to get somewhat repetitive, which I feel the game designer — Shelly Alon, who developed this game singlehandedly — was likely aware of. Completed levels form constellations (out of planets, not stars), and the game ends after just 65 planets — setting itself apart from content-vomiters like &lt;em&gt;Candy Crush&lt;/em&gt; — and doesn&amp;rsquo;t force players to replay levels extensively to achieve some unlikely high score. Instead, there are challenges to complete levels under a (generous) time limit, and to do so in the minimum possible number of robot moves, providing a shallow level of replayability for those who want it.&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-sputnik-eyes/constellation_huec79b848a40fbc6e180e238cf7544ebf_147126_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-sputnik-eyes/constellation_huec79b848a40fbc6e180e238cf7544ebf_147126_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;1136&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, &lt;em&gt;Sputnik Eyes&lt;/em&gt; is a satisfying puzzle game resulting from heartfelt, thoughtful work that turns a hopeful eye to what lies beyond our atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
