<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pixel-art | Joshua J. Daymude</title>
    <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/pixel-art/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/pixel-art/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>pixel-art</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2022 Joshua J. Daymude</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 12:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jdaymude.github.io/media/logo_hu1dc8deb1865675db905a286e8af9308b_16380_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url>
      <title>pixel-art</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/tag/pixel-art/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Undertale</title>
      <link>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-undertale/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 12:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-undertale/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every review for Toby Fox&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Undertale&lt;/em&gt; seems to somehow impart a deep seeded conviction that this truly is one of the most emotional, clever, unexpected games of all time. That conviction is so powerful that by the time I metaphorically pulled this title off the shelf and gave it a good dusting (months after I got it as a much wanted gift), the idea that I was going to be blown away by this little indie game was all but a concrete expectation. That hope only grew when, after falling in love with &amp;ldquo;His Theme&amp;rdquo; when it was used as a backing track behind some &lt;em&gt;Overwatch&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NjgokkTtniY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;voice lines&lt;/a&gt;, I found &lt;em&gt;Undertale&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s soundtrack to be incredible in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps by osmosis, I had come to respect the vague, sacred secrecy the community held around the game&amp;rsquo;s details. But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until I fired it up for the first time that I realized I&amp;rsquo;d never even seen a screenshot of &lt;em&gt;Undertale&lt;/em&gt; before, and it was honestly a jarring experience. Playing on my 3000x2000 Surface Book display, &lt;em&gt;Undertale&lt;/em&gt; loaded as a little box of pixel graphics that only occupied a ninth of my screen, and it took me a solid amount of Googling to figure out if it even had a fullscreen mode (it does, press &lt;code&gt;F4&lt;/code&gt;). Once it was big enough to actually see, it was a whole other struggle to figure out how to control stuff, as &lt;em&gt;Undertale&lt;/em&gt; offers you no real tutorial whatsoever (arrow keys to walk, and &lt;code&gt;Z&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;X&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;Ctrl&lt;/code&gt; for pretty much everything else). In fact, the initial feeling I had was one of deflation; this supposedly perfect game was actually a time machine back to the days of pixel art and text-based RPGs with a bad on-ramping experience.&lt;/p&gt;














&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /review/videogame-undertale/judgement_hu6a228774f549573fbecc8eaf41cdd971_135799_a8bf3ae1caf1acd05114557c3803998a.png 400w,
               /review/videogame-undertale/judgement_hu6a228774f549573fbecc8eaf41cdd971_135799_9860648261eeaae0d8c5cdd6d9ad53b4.png 760w,
               /review/videogame-undertale/judgement_hu6a228774f549573fbecc8eaf41cdd971_135799_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://jdaymude.github.io/review/videogame-undertale/judgement_hu6a228774f549573fbecc8eaf41cdd971_135799_a8bf3ae1caf1acd05114557c3803998a.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;428&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that brings us to the paradox of &lt;em&gt;Undertale&lt;/em&gt;: in order to give it all the praise it deserves, to show off all the things that make it both sharply witty and warmly endearing, and to convince a newcomer to push past the honestly confounding first 10 minutes of play, I&amp;rsquo;d have to spoil a little of the game. And that is something I should absolutely not do. Because realizing what &lt;em&gt;Undertale&lt;/em&gt; is, living out the experience of a truly beautiful game revealing itself to you in the subtlest of character dialogue, and feeling your assumptions about how it should be played slip away — all of this must be yours and only yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So have a little hope, press on, and stay determined. You&amp;rsquo;ll be so happy you did.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
